There are twelve of them.
Twelve stadiums built in the four corners of Europe.
Conceived by the most daring architects and built by thousands of workers and engineers.
Twelve gigantic arenas selected to host matches for a global event,
the 2020 European Football Championship.
Embark on a unique tour of Europe to discover the most beautiful stadiums on the continent.
In this episode,
Danden Park Stadium in Glasgow, Scotland versus Aviva Stadium in Dublin, Ireland.
On one hand,
a stadium built in 1903,
which has successfully reinvented itself over time and has hosted international sporting events and monumental concerts.
which has successfully reinvented itself over time and has hosted international sporting events.
and monumental concerts.
He holds a special place.
It's a national treasure.
When it is full,
The atmosphere is incredible.
On the other hand,
a stadium that was completely destroyed and then rebuilt.
A cutting-edge speaker.
completely unique
which had to adapt to the site's multiple requirements,
right in the heart of Dublin city.
The challenge,
That was the size of the site.
We had to exploit it to the fullest and constantly push its limits.
We had to exploit it to the fullest.
to the maximum and constantly push the limits.
Two legendary stadiums,
Glasgow and Dublin.
Let's begin our journey in Scotland and its largest city with 600,000 inhabitants.
Glasgow.
Located in the west-central part of the country,
This working-class city has lost none of its splendor despite the economic decline of the 1960s.
From industrial architecture to Victorian architecture,
Glasgow has undergone multiple changes.
And one monument alone symbolizes the history of the city.
its stadium,
Anden Park.
This legendary stadium,
rooted in collective memory,
It has existed for over 120 years.
But it has undergone great transformations over time.
Richard McBreaty,
curator of the national football museum,
He knows all the details.
Located within the stadium grounds,
The museum retraces the memorable history of Scottish football.
starting with the first international match which pitted Scotland against England.
It is the team from the amateur club Queen's Park that represents the Scottish national team.
England came to play against Scotland on a cricket pitch because in 1872,
Indoor football stadiums did not yet exist in Glasgow.
The match was a huge success.
It is talked about as the trigger for the explosion of football.
A few months later,
in March 1872,
In 1873,
The Scottish Football Association is created.
The Scottish Cup was established and that's really thanks to Queen's Park club which played a major role in bringing together the first clubs.
Faced with such success,
The Queen's Park team wants to reunite.
To acquire a stadium worthy of the name, in 1873 she built Amden 1, which could accommodate 20,000 spectators.
but ten years later the installation of a railway line forced the team to move in 1884 the second Amden Park with a capacity of 25,000 spectators was inaugurated.
And in 1903, a third, even larger stadium was built, capable of holding up to 40,000 fans.
capable of accommodating up to 40,000 fans.
Richard takes us to the site of the legendary former Hamden 2 stadium.
Richard takes us to the site of the legendary former Hamden stadium.
2. There,
There,
We are at the site of the current Katkin Park.
But before 1903,
This was the second Hamden Park.
The Queen's Park club was based here from 1884 to 1903.
We know that the ground level was much lower and that the old grandstand ran the entire length of the pitch on that side.
at the time of Hamden Park 2.
We know that the main building was on that side,
in the corner,
at the far right.
We have the photos.
You can really do everything on foot in 10 minutes.
From Hamden Park stadium,
We arrive at the sites of the two former Hamden Parks.
It's really very close.
It is therefore in this extremely restricted territory that the great history of Scottish football was written.
In 1902,
A tragedy will change the way stadiums are designed and built.
Highbrox Stadium,
another stadium in the city,
is the scene of a tragedy.
During the Scotland-England match,
Part of the wooden structure collapsed and 26 people died.
To prevent such an accident from occurring in the new facility,
The designers of the third Amden have therefore decided to revise their plan.
When the stadium was inaugurated in
In 1903, we can really see that it differs from previous models.
The natural basin on which it is built was constructed in 1903.
ensure tiered seating with a solid structure.
Safety barriers are installed to prevent certain areas from becoming too crowded.
SO,
we see appearing in...
In Hamden Park,
systems of steel cables stretched between concrete poles that are used to control the impressive crowds that come to the game.
Upon its opening,
with a capacity of 40,000 seats,
Hamden Park, the third, is the largest football stadium in the world.
Over the years,
It transforms,
It is expanding and modernizing to accommodate even more spectators.
In 1937,
It breaks all records with 149,415 people.
But in 1950,
It is dethroned by the Maracana stadium and its 200,000 spectators.
Another stadium is also steeped in history.
The Viva Stadium,
formerly Lansdowne Road stadium in Dublin.
Unlike Amden Park,
The Irish enclosure has always remained in the same place.
But the builders had to overcome many challenges to modernize it,
But the builders had to overcome many challenges to modernize it while adapting it to the site.
while adapting to the site.
Here,
Here in Ireland,
in Ireland,
on the edge of the legendary Lansdowne Road,
This stadium is a true institution.
Built in 1872,
This stadium initially hosted two of the city's football clubs and the national rugby team.
before also becoming,
since the 1980s,
the official stadium of the national football team.
If, over the course of the 20th century,
Lansdowne Road stadium has undergone various renovations,
at the dawn of the 2000s,
It is outdated.
It must be completely destroyed in order to be rebuilt.
It was an old stadium with only 24,000 seats.
And the rest of the crowd,
that is 26,000 people.
remained standing.
So it was difficult to manage.
So in 2004 we decided that we needed a new stadium.
For football authorities and for the fans,
That's obvious.
The new enclosure must be built in exactly the same place as the previous one.
But this site is particularly complex.
The stadium is located in the very heart of the urban fabric.
2 km from the city centre.
To the east,
The Doder river forms a natural boundary.
A railway line crosses the site from north to south.
It connects Dublin to Rossler.
port of connection to the United Kingdom and all of Europe.
And all around,
The area is bordered by residential neighborhoods.
But to comply with the new hospitality standards in a stadium,
Its size must increase by 51%.
SO,
How can such a large stadium be fitted into such a small area?
The task facing manufacturers is proving to be immense.
especially since the constraints are numerous.
I would say that this is surely the most complex site that designers have ever had to deal with when installing a stadium.
If the stadium were oriented east-west,
The north and south stands would border the residential areas more closely.
would cast their shadows on the houses and disturb more residents.
It would also encroach on the adjacent rugby training ground, which must absolutely be preserved.
Architects therefore have no choice,
The stadium's orientation must be north-south.
This new layout is perfectly suited to the site.
But with only three access points,
We need to create new ones.
And significant work is essential.
The promenade along the river has been improved and widened.
creating a fourth access point.
A new structure spans the railway line that divides the site in two, forming a podium that provides a fifth access point.
At Swan Lane,
A house belonging to the city of Dublin is being demolished to allow for a sixth and final access.
All of this is completely reshaping the neighborhood.
From now on,
The river is bordered by a promenade that benefits all city residents.
even outside of match days.
However, the new orientation and access points do not make the stadium design any easier.
The shape of the new stadium in Viva is unique.
Firstly, because it adapts to the site.
We needed to create the highest possible tiered seating structure because that's what creates the atmosphere.
But it was also necessary to ensure that the stadium blended in with the surrounding environment.
the city,
the residential area.
This accumulation of restrictions led us to choose a solution that is truly satisfactory.
The proximity of dwellings will therefore play a determining role in the shape of the arena.
The residential areas to the south and north do not allow for the construction of a very tall structure.
The houses adjoining the site are only one or two stories high and look very tiny compared to the typical stadium height of 50 or 60 meters.
The houses adjoining the site are only one or two stories high and look very tiny compared to the typical stadium height.
which can reach up to 50 or 60 meters in height.
To avoid damaging homes,
The shadow cast by the stadium, and therefore its height, must be minimal.
For architects,
The room for maneuver is extremely limited.
The height of the north facade must not exceed 24.45 m.
It is referred to as the first stadium that adapts to its site.
particularly well integrated into its position in Dublin.
One of its most beautiful features,
It's the asymmetry of its design,
along different axes.
It gives it a unique identity.
It is therefore the site constraints that have shaped the DNA of the stadium,
It is therefore the site constraints that have shaped the DNA of the stadium, giving it this very specific futuristic design.
giving it that very specific futuristic look.
If the stadium blends perfectly with the neighborhood,
It also adapts to the city and its environment.
The architectural intention was to create an ephemeral form in the city skyline reminiscent of the hills south of Dublin.
The final result respects history.
He respects the city.
Many buildings in
17th, 18th and
19th century buildings in Dublin have domed roofs.
That's definitely one of the city's defining characteristics.
Dublin is a fairly low-lying city.
So, by a long shot.
We can see bell towers,
domes and other shapes that make up the city's rooftops.
And now,
The Aviva stadium is just one of those forms.
Architects and engineers continue to find solutions to the many obstacles that arise.
But their troubles are not over yet.
Dublin can be prone to flooding and the water table is very high.
in many places around the city and especially on our website.
Having high groundwater levels is always a problem for builders.
We need to build in dry ground.
The ground needs to be dried out in order to dig.
This is the only way to build safely and quickly.
At this location,
The water table is only 2 or 3 meters underground.
To build the stadium,
The engineers therefore chose to start in the summer so that the ground would be as dry as possible.
They designed specific foundations to allow the stadium to be firmly anchored in the ground.
The builders drove piles into a layer of solid soil 25 meters deep.
The presence of such an enclosure significantly alters the drainage of rainwater that could otherwise cause the river to overflow.
To avoid this,
The builders designed a gigantic reservoir under the stadium.
Located to the east,
It's right under the grandstand.
On the roof,
Gutters collect the rain and carry the water to the reservoir through a network of pipes.
They store the water and control the amount released into the river that runs alongside the stadium.
This ingenious system helps to avoid the risk of canal or river overflowing.
When designing such structures,
Hundreds of parameters need to be taken into account.
And the rain factor should not be overlooked.
Definitely not in Dublin.
In Glasgow too,
It rains very regularly.
In the 1990s,
Work to cover all the stands has finally begun.
The stadium needed to be modernized for safety reasons.
Better crowd control,
Reduce crowds and increase overall security.
Reduce crowds.
and increase security in general,
and also to design a more welcoming environment for spectators,
So they can watch football matches protected by a roof rather than being exposed.
So they can watch football matches protected by a roof.
than being exposed.
The stadium rehabilitation work took place in two phases.
First of all,
the roof of the north and east stands,
then the west and south stands.
The overall structure of the roof is a system of cantilevered beams.
To cover the entire seating area and therefore all spectators,
A framework up to 42 meters long had to be designed.
A framework extending to the very bottom had to be designed.
up to 42 meters long.
To balance such an overhang,
the load-bearing structures must be particularly strong.
The engineers therefore installed two concrete columns per section.
One at the rear of the stands and one at the periphery of the stadium act as counterweights and prevent the roof from tilting forward.
One at the rear of the stands,
and one at the rear of the stands.
One on the periphery of the stadium that serves as a counterweight and prevents the roof from tilting forward.
The pillars are firmly anchored in the ground.
And the unique feature of this roof,
That's its curvature.
The south stand is higher than the others.
The engineers therefore adapted the shape of the roof to create a harmonious whole.
It was a challenge,
But it was just geometry.
We had to pay attention to the geometry.
in design,
at the different levels of the stands and in the design of the roof beams to create this raised profile above the south stand.
To cover the new roof,
Engineers need to find the ideal material.
Its surface area is very large and the space in the center is very small.
The drawback,
This prevents the lawn from receiving enough light to grow.
The front part of the roof that overlooks the south stands,
west and partially to the east is translucent.
This allows natural light to pass through to the lawn so that it is not constantly in shadow.
So it facilitates grass growth by letting light through.
There are few materials that can offer this level of transparency, and the plastic we have chosen offers the ideal level of transparency.
And it's an inexpensive solution.
In terms of design,
We drew our inspiration from nature.
It gives it a nice appearance.
So it's a combination of aesthetic criteria,
Functionality and cost led us to choose this material for the roof.
Functionality and cost.
which led us to choose this material to cover the roof.
Weather is a key factor in the design of the Scottish stadium.
The materials must be perfectly chosen so that the structure does not degrade prematurely.
So,
The roof beams are made of Corten steel.
corrosion-resistant steel.
Corten steel is a specific steel alloy that contains a lot of copper and nickel.
This chemical composition gives the steel weather-resistant properties.
Steel oxidizes when exposed to air.
It creates this brown patina,
A uniform color across the entire roof,
A uniform color across the entire roof that protects the steel from the elements and eliminates the need for painting.
which protects the steel against the elements and avoids the need to paint it.
But the engineers didn't choose Corten steel solely for its strength.
Corten steel is slightly more expensive than normal raw steel.
but it doesn't require any painting.
When you look at the roof,
We can see that there must be approximately 2000 tonnes of steel.
even more
across this entire area.
This saved a lot of money.
in the range of 200,000 to 250,000 pounds.
in the range of 200,000.
to 250,000 pounds.
The completion of the roof at the level of the south stand marked the end of the work on the entire stand at the end of the 90s.
It has become the stadium's premier stand.
The south stand is the main stand at Hamden.
We have ensured that the quality of the facilities in this area is optimal.
while the other three stands were designed as simple bleachers.
The new stand accommodates a third of the stadium's spectators and provides high-quality services.
In addition to the spectator reception areas,
new spaces for VIP guests,
the press,
The media and the players are designed.
A conference room.
A clinic specializing in sports.
The Museum of France.
The National Football Museum.
of the National Front.
A warm-up room just steps away from the changing rooms.
An internal underground road is even installed to allow secure access for teams and VIP spectators.
On the sixth floor of the grandstand,
Nearly 3000 m² of office space houses the most influential administrations and institutions of Scottish football.
But this highly diverse offering requires finding space while maintaining a harmonious overall structure.
The stadium was built in a natural basin located on a sloping piece of land.
The lawn is therefore one story below ground level in the south and two stories below in the north.
The architects took advantage of this existing slope.
The architects used this existing slope to create two lower levels beneath the south stand.
to construct two lower floors below the south stand.
To accommodate even more people,
They decided to add two upper floors which even offer an additional grandstand level.
The roof of the south stand is two levels higher than that of the north stand.
This particular curvature has thus become one of the iconic features of Amden Park stadium.
The extensive renovations undertaken on the roof and the south stand have given a new lease of life to this national stadium, which hosts major sporting events and internationally renowned concerts every year.
The extensive renovations undertaken on the roof and the south stand have given a new lease of life to this national stadium, which hosts major sporting events every year.
but also internationally renowned concerts.
In Dublin,
The architects and engineers successfully adapted to the site and designed a majestic work.
Outside the stadium is the smallest stand with only 14 rows.
To the east and to the west,
The facades are much more imposing.
It is the building's overall asymmetry that makes it so unique.
Geometry is the founding principle of engineering.
But here,
Controlling irregularity and asymmetry required great precision.
very quickly,
and to be able to adapt to a variety of situations.
exteriors.
For example,
one of the most interesting parts of the overall structure of the stadium,
These are the cantilevered levels that extend 4 to 4.5 meters beyond the perimeter of the stadium.
These cantilevers located all around the stadium play a major role in its design.
On the west side,
They are present on three levels.
from the fifth to the seventh floor.
On the east side,
They are present on six levels,
are present on six levels,
from the second to the seventh floor.
This ingenious system allows for more space to be created on each upper level while minimizing the stadium's overall footprint.
This ingenious system allows for more space to be created on each upper level,
while minimizing the overall footprint of the stadium on the ground.
On the upper floors,
Spectators have a sense of closeness to the outside world and a secret link between the stadium and the city.
To support these cantilevers,
The architects design special columns.
On each floor,
Each column is specifically adapted to the structure.
One on top of the other,
All of these columns together seem to form an imposing pillar spanning the entire stadium.
To limit the extent of the cantilevers,
which create the external curvature of the stadium,
We also bent our columns.
parallel to the outline of the enclosure.
These columns are highlighted and are visible in certain places from the outside and of course when walking around inside.
They are truly part of the stadium's identity.
To adapt to this unique geometric shape,
To this unique geometric shape,
The engineers had to design different column shapes for each floor.
The most original ones are V-shaped.
They are located in the southeast and southwest corners of the stadium.
In the roof design,
In
the roof design,
here too,
The architects favoured unusual curves.
Result,
an architectural gem that makes this roof one of the emblems of the stadium.
That makes it a very beautiful work.
this facade.
The complexity of the techniques used and the technical integrity of its architecture,
This is extremely important.
There is a real link between aesthetics,
the architectural intention and the technical detail.
To avoid obstructing the spectators' view,
The designers have created a highly ingenious structure.
The main structure of the roof is composed of three major elements.
The outer beam that runs all around the perimeter of the stadium and is supported by the building itself.
Then
14 secondary beams that connect this structure to the third element,
14 secondary beams.
which connects this structure to the third element, the main horseshoe-shaped beam, rests on the general structure of the stadium and on the two large and unique concrete columns located to the north for
the main beam.
Horseshoe-shaped,
It rests on the general structure of the stadium and on the two large and unique concrete columns located to the north.
To cover the entire stadium,
tertiary beams are installed above the main roof structure to support polycarbonate panels
Tertiary beams are installed above the main roof structure,
in order to receive polycarbonate panels.
Once the roof design is complete,
It needs to be assembled.
A major challenge for manufacturers,
because the main structure functions as a single unit,
which requires meticulous and spectacular organization.
To avoid using too many temporary towers on the site,
The engineers put in place a specific plan to use only 6 of them.
They divided the entire structure into 15 sections to be built.
The last section,
that of the north stand,
is independent.
The initial arrangement of the temporary towers allows the main roof structure to be built up to section 6 and the roofing installation to begin on the first two sections.
Afterwards,
only two laps,
those closest to the starting point,
are moved to another point because they are no longer useful.
With this new configuration,
Assembly can continue.
Assembly can continue and reach section 8 for the main structure and section 5 for the roof.
and reach section 8 for the main structure and section 5 for the roof.
Again,
The two central towers are moved to a new strategic location.
The main roof structure is almost entirely installed up to section 13 and the roofing is installed up to section 8.
The final arrangement,
by moving two towers,
allows the main structure and roof to be fully completed.
Only four temporary tower movements were required to keep the structure in the air during its construction.
The roof of the north stand can then be built,
The temporary towers are dismantled and the roof is finally finished.
Part of this structure is now supported by the two megapillars inside the stadium.
A huge gamble for an extraordinary piece of architecture.
And to cover the stadium,
Architects and engineers have chosen a material that must be in perfect harmony with its environment.
Normally,
Raw polycarbonate is yellow.
To make it transparent,
It needs to be dyed blue.
And in our case,
We decided to tint it blue to ensure the transparency lasts.
but also to create a range of blue colors that diffuse inside the stadium.
Some panels are facing upwards,
Thus they reflect it.
and the stadium's envelope blends completely with the sky.
The visual impact of the stadium is thus extremely reduced.
But when you look at the signs that are lower down,
They are oriented towards the ground.
And so they allow a level of transparency that enables people to understand the stadium and its structure as a whole.
Therefore, the builders will use polycarbonate to construct this facade to give it this very particular architectural profile.
The engineers designed aluminum bars that adapt to the vertical shape of the stadium.
15,000 double metal axle supports are fixed to these bars.
Polycarbonate panels,
on average one meter by three
are attached and aligned on these supports.
This system allows for obtaining a highly specific profile.
What's important about the dual support,
It allows you to change the position and fix the panels.
This gives us the possibility to create long curves all along the stadium.
And all of this allows us to realize the architectural intention,
which was to echo the Dublin hills and surround the stadium with an ephemeral envelope.
The function of these 5000 polycarbonate panels is not solely to contribute to the architectural brilliance of the enclosure.
We have two types of polycarbonate around the stadium.
The one on the roof is made up of several gutters that collect the water and join the outer contours of the stadium.
This one is waterproof.
On the facade,
It's a completely different type of polycarbonate.
Making it waterproof was pointless.
The stadium needed to be protected.
the corridors where people circulate,
reduce the impact of the wind and reduce the temperature.
That's why there are two different types of polycarbonate.
And the line that separates them is actually the main gutter that goes around the stadium.
And that's what you can see when you approach Lansdowne Road and catch sight of the stadium.
And that's what you can see when you approach Lansdowne Road and catch sight of the Aviva Stadium.
You can clearly see these two structures, which are made of solid polycarbonate and tinted blue.
You can clearly see these two structures, which are made of solid polycarbonate.
and dyed blue.
By constructing this facade,
The architects and engineers have achieved a remarkable feat.
They managed to reconcile aesthetics and technique.
This facade with its intricate lines has become the symbol of the stadium and contributes to its international renown.
Which is commendable,
that is, wherever you are in the city,
You can see the stadium for miles around.
Because there is always a panel that will reflect the sun towards where you are.
regardless of your location,
You will always see a small ray of sunshine reflected by the stadium.
It's something special.
which makes the stadium different from almost all other buildings at the University of Paris.
which makes the stadium different from almost all other buildings in the city.
The city, the complexity of the roof—it's one of the most complex and successful roofs we've designed so far, of all the stadiums we've built. To have achieved this is truly remarkable.
The complexity of the roof,
That's for now.
of all the stadiums we've designed so far,
one of the most complex and accomplished covers.
And to manage to do that,
It's really good.
In Glasgow,
in Amden Park stadium, most of the facilities and
in Amden Park stadium,
Most facilities and services are located in the south stand.
The service is located in the south stand.
The north stand,
She,
was old and poorly laid out.
It was time to undertake major works.
where we are currently located,
had to be renovated in 2012.
We realized that the spectators were not satisfied with this stand, which was far too crowded.
We wanted more space for the toilets,
food and drink stalls,
install some elevators and also new spaces for all those who come to watch the football matches.
So the comfort of the spectators in the North Stand has really been improved.
The stadium decides to act,
especially since in 2014,
Scotland is hosting the Commonwealth Games,
an international competition that attracts great athletes and many spectators.
Therefore, the surface area of ​​the north stand needs to be increased.
but the remaining available space is very limited.
In this area,
The stadium is bordered by Somerville Drive.
And on the other side of the street,
a few meters from the perimeter,
there is a residential area.
The architects therefore optimized the space and used every available square centimeter.
The outer wall of the north stand forms an oblique angle with Somerville Drive.
This configuration offers the opportunity to create an exceptional facade.
To reinforce this visual distinctiveness,
The architects built a long wall with edges fitted with huge panes of glass.
The facade is spectacular and allows sunlight to penetrate.
Sunlight can penetrate from the east and west.
So there is a lot of sun at the beginning and end of the day.
There is an amazing evolution of the light throughout the day,
without disturbing the neighborhood.
If this facade is a benchmark of modernity,
The architects also wanted to incorporate a strong symbolic and historical element.
The facade design is really interesting.
We wanted to remind everyone that this is Scotland's national stadium.
We had the idea of ​​using tartan.
It's a very Scottish pattern.
We didn't want the tartan to be too bold.
We didn't want...
We didn't want it to be too obvious either.
We didn't want it to look like a kilt either.
The pattern was stylized with shades of blue.
And it's not just the color that changes,
but also the texture of the panels.
This is an idea that symbolizes tartan.
but without being exactly like a kilt.
One of the key points was to preserve the iconic drum-shaped staircases of Amden Park.
One of the key points.
The aim was to preserve the drum-shaped staircases.
iconic of Amden Park.
These are circular staircases with glass brick walls.
It was really very characteristic.
We didn't really want to cover them up.
But we had no choice.
So we tried to find a solution to ensure they would still be present.
We left them as they were.
but they were painted in different colors to help people moving around the stadium find their way.
When moving around inside the stands,
The curves of the stairs can still be seen.
We haven't lost them.
They still exist and they have been brought to the forefront.
Even celebrated,
if you will.
In addition to its historical value,
Its stepped columns lend an original dynamism to the space,
these stepped columns lend an original dynamism to the space,
like waves.
Finally,
The architects had one last mission to accomplish,
to renovate the ground floor, the facade of which is right up against the road.
To facilitate the movement of supporters,
a large hall was created at ground level.
In a football stadium,
What's interesting,
The problem is that you have to manage a lot of people.
who enters,
who is coming out,
And all of this must take place in the football stadium.
And all of this must take place in comfort and safety.
in comfort and safety.
That's why we decided to build the first level and leave the ground floor available.
like a large hall,
an outdoor area where people can wait to enter the stadium.
What's really practical,
What's true.
It's because they are safe.
And obviously,
when the weather is bad,
That's definitely an advantage.
The architects and engineers took up the challenge of building,
in such a small space,
a very functional and aesthetically pleasing extension.
It has become a landmark for the people of Glasgow.
It has become a landmark for the people of Glasgow, and to host the Commonwealth Games, a
And to host the Commonwealth Games,
An unusual modification has been made.
The venue is equipped only with a pitch with a lawn.
Gold for this multisport competition,
Gold,
for this multisport competition,
The International Association of Athletics Federations requires a regulation track of 400 meters.
When it was proposed that Amden be prepared for the Commonwealth Games,
I thought it was going to be a very interesting technical challenge.
And I was very happy to have the chance to participate.
The solution chosen by the authorities is a platform placed on stilts at a height of 2 meters.
It meets the required technical and safety standards.
But before construction can begin,
There is one last step to validate.
One of the biggest challenges of the project was persuading people,
and in particular athletes,
that a platform would not be fragile,
and that in reality,
It would feel like being on the ground.
because it was anchored in the ground.
And so,
to reassure the athletes,
A model was reproduced in Glasgow.
in a street and on a slight bend.
We built a whole athletics track and let them run on it just to prove to them that it worked very well and that they would not feel any movement or vibration and that everything would seem normal to them.
Once this system is approved by top athletes,
The work begins.
They removed 8000 seats and the lawn.
The platform will be made up of 1000 plywood panels supported by 6000 steel columns.
The 400-meter athletics track and the lawn are installed on top.
We are going from a plot of land of 7200 square meters to an area of ​​18500 square meters.
16,000 tons of materials are used to complete the construction.
16,000 tons of materials are used to finalize the installation.
and to finalize the installation.
A drainage system is being put in place.
The existing electrical system is disconnected and a new one is installed.
The platform was built in 28 weeks and completed less than 10 weeks before the opening of the Commonwealth Games.
In its final configuration,
The capacity is 43,000 people compared to 51,000 in normal times.
Once the games are over,
The structure has been dismantled.
Amden Park has returned to its usual configuration.
Anden Park has returned to its usual configuration.
Hamden Park Stadium,
Amden Park Stadium,
the true cradle of football,
It has managed to transcend the centuries and become part of the great history of football.
It has managed to transcend the centuries and become part of the great history of the blue ball.
Hamden Park is Scotland's national stadium.
The current Hamden has been there since 1903.
It represents something very special for the Scots.
The Aviva Stadium has reinvented itself to become a remarkable piece of futuristic architecture.
The stadium was meant to be an icon.
The Irish needed to be able to be proud of it.
The Aviva Stadium is instantly recognizable, and that's what we wanted.
Two magical stadiums that attract fans from all over the world.